<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An apology for the honorable nation of the Jevvs, and all the sons of Israel· Written by Edward Nicholas, Gent.</title>
            <author>Nicholas, Edward.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89670</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N1081</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E544_16</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203014</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863118</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863118</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115300</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89670)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115300)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 84:E544[16])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An apology for the honorable nation of the Jevvs, and all the sons of Israel· Written by Edward Nicholas, Gent.</title>
                  <author>Nicholas, Edward.</author>
                  <author>Manasseh ben Israel, 1604-1657, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Field,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648 [i.e. 1649]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Nothing is known about Edward Nicholas, who was once thought to be identical with Sir Edward Nicholas (1593-1669). Some authorities consider the name a pseudonym, disguising, perhaps, Manasseh ben Israel. Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "feb: 21".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jews --  Great Britain --  Social conditions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115300:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN APOLOGY FOR THE HONORABLE NATION OF THE JEWS, And all the SONS of ISRAEL. Written by <hi>Edward Nicholas,</hi> Gent.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſaiah 14.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>For Jehovah will have compaſsion of Jacob, and will yet chuſe Iſrael, and cauſe them to reſt in their own land, and the ſtranger ſhall joyn himſelf unto them, and they ſhall cleave to the houſe of Jacob.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Deut. 23.39.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Happy art thou O Iſrael: who is like unto thee, O people! ſaved by Jehovah, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Jer. 30.7.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Alas for that day is great, ſo that none is like it; it is even the time of Jacobs trouble, but he ſhall be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from it.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Jer. 31.14, 15, 16, 17.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Thus ſaith Jehovah, A voyce was heard in Ramah, lamentation and bitter weeping, Rachel weeping for her children, refuſed to be comforted becauſe they were not: Thus ſaith Jehovah, Refrain thy voyce from weeping, and thine eyes from tears, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Field,</hi> 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="apology">
            <pb facs="tcp:115300:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:115300:2"/>
            <head>AN APOLOGY For the Honorable Nation OF THE JEWS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat our Nation of <hi>England</hi> hath already ſuffered much affliction, and that we yet labor under many burthens, fears, and doubtings, what will be the ſequel, is a thing ſo clear, that lamentable experience doth abundantly teſtifie.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that are in authority in this kingdom, and we all, may make the application; that the crying ſins of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion do call for vengeance, which we have juſt cauſe to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, unleſs we meet God by repentance, and ſatisfaction of the oppreſſed.</p>
            <p>To undertake to ſpeak of the many groſs and loud crying ſins we lie under the guilt of, were to leſſen them; they are ſo many, 'twere better to be ſilent, then to uſe few words in rehearſing them that are ſo odious to God, leaſt we ſeem to extenuate them: I ſhall confine my ſelf to two, The oppreſſion of the poor, And the perſecution of the Saints of God. As for the firſt, I hope that the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of affairs (wherein we are involved) have interupted
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115300:3"/>(partly) good and pious intentions: The ſufferings of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the faithful friends of the Parliament have been great, and muſt needs vent themſelves by ſome complaints, and the rather, ſeeing our good God hath forgiven Ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Talents, as by their great, if not miraculous ſucceſſes ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, yet every cruel ſervant takes his brother by the throat for ſmall matters, and exacting the utmoſt uſury (which in quiet and peaceable times is contrary to the Law, as I humbly conceive by ſome Statute appears) not allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the freedom to walk on the Lords-day, and to joyn themſelves with ſuch Congregations of Gods people for the refreſhment of their ſouls, amidſt their ſufferings in the outward man, as they deſire to do.</p>
            <p>But the ſin principally intended here, is, The ſtrict and cruel Laws now in force againſt the moſt honorable Nation of the world, the Nation of the Jews, a people choſen by God, as appears by the many and large expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of his favor to them, ſtiling them, <hi>His Gems, his firſt-born, a precious people above all peoples of the earth, a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of prieſts, an holy people unto himſelf:</hi> And further ſaith, they are his own ſervants, and ſhould not be in bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage to any, being onely to ſerve ſix years, and the ſeventh to go out free, and in the year of Jubile, every man was to return to his inheritance: But above all, that pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of theirs, the benefit whereof hath an influence on all the faithful, and redounds to their happineſs, <hi>That in thee and thy ſeed ſhall all the nations of the earth be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed:</hi> So ſtrong an obligation are we bound in to them through Gods mercy.</p>
            <p>And now let all the faithful ſervants of God take to their conſiderations, how great indurings that honorable Nation hath ſuffered, what bloody ſlaughters have been made of them in <hi>London,</hi> in the North countrey of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and divers other parts of this kingdom; and how they have been proſcribed and baniſht this kingdom, and denyed that commerce allowed to all others, even to bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115300:3"/>Infidels; ſo that the tranſcendency of this ſin is not to be paralleld, in regard they being ſo honorably ſtiled and owned by God himſelf, in rejecting them, we highly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe the Majeſty of Jehovah: whereas we ought rather to honor them whom God honoreth, and to have a grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful remembrance of thoſe people of God, by whom he hath conveyed to his people ſo great bleſſings and incomparable priviledges, to comfort the afflicted, and not to take the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, when God was angry with them, to help for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the affliction. In their next place, if we would but follow the politicians rule, that aym onely at their own ends and gains <hi>(proh dolor)</hi> that may prove, and will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be an advantage to us divers ways, and on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, moſt dangerous to this kingdom, for that the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of all men is in Gods people, whoſe bleſſings are continually ſhowred down on a Land for their ſakes, of whom are theſe a part that we have thus abandoned. It was a notable obſervation of a reverend and godly learned Preacher, before this Parliament, on this Text, <hi>Touch not mine anointed, and do my prophets no harm, Pſal.</hi> 105.15. That the good or evil uſage of Gods people, is the greateſt State-intereſt in the world: how great cauſe have we then to lay this to our hearts, the godly can beſt judge.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, beſides the judgements of God, which our Forefathers have felt by bloody Wars, and other miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, we at this time have experience of many calamities; and now the years of recompence are approaching, which we have cauſe to believe, when we read of the many com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations of God, againſt the ſpoilers and oppreſſors of his people the Jews, as Jer. 30.16. <hi>Therefore, all they that devour thee, ſhall be devoured and all thine adverſaries, every one of them ſhall go into captivity; and they that ſpoil thee, ſhall be a ſpoil, and all that prey upon thee, will I give for a prey:</hi> and Iſa. 33.1. and 34.1. to 8. and 41.11. <hi>Behold, all that were incenſed againſt thee, ſhall be aſhamed and confounded, they ſhall be as nothing, and they that ſtrive with thee, ſhall
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115300:4"/>periſh,</hi> and ſo to the end; and 49.25. <hi>Even the captives of the mighty ſhall be taken away, and the prey of the terrible ſhall be delivered, for I will contend with him that contendeth with thee, and I will ſave thy children: And I will feed them that oppreſs thee with their own fleſh, and they ſhall be drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with their own blood, as with ſweet wine, and all fleſh ſhall know, that I am thy Savior and Redeemer, the mighty one of Jacob:</hi> and Jer. 25.31. and <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51.22, 23. and 60.14. and 61.3, 4.</p>
            <p>'Tis Objected, The great guilt that lies on the Jews for crucifying Chriſt, and that therefore, and for refuſing the Goſpel, they are rejected of God, ſo unworthy of favor, aſſiſtance, and compaſſion herein deſired. In Anſwer, though this be imputed to the whole Nation, yet it is apparent in the Goſpel, that that action was done by the Elders, chief Prieſts, and Scribes, his Doctrine reproving their Hypocrifie, and lazineſs and pride, that they wrought a faction againſt him, and not that the whole Nation were guilty; for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ere-while brought him into the city, crying, <hi>Hoſanna:</hi> And its ſaid, when Jeſus was condemned by <hi>Pilate,</hi> and the chief Prieſts and Elders, that they perſwaded the people to refuſe Jeſus, and to chooſe <hi>Barrabas:</hi> 'tis probable that they are ſo well verſd in their own buſineſs of ſo high a nature, that they can ſay more for themſelves: It is too great an undertaking for me, and will require a larger Tract, to clear the matter againſt all Objections, which may be done by men of more learning then I profeſs to have; the regal Government of the Jews being long before ended: what God in his ſecret will and judgement intended in the ſcattering of the Jews, I preſume not to underſtand or to gueſs at: my purpoſe is onely to prove, That God yet owns them for his people, and though caſt off for a time, yet their certain future reduction is promiſed, as <hi>Paul,</hi> in <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.24, 25, 26. <hi>For if thou waſt cut out of the olive-tree which was wilde by nature, and waſt grafted contrary to nature in a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115300:4"/>right olive-tree, how much more ſhall they that are by nature, be grafted in their own olive-tree? For I would not, bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, that ye ſhould be ignorant of this ſecret</hi> (leſt ye ſhould be arrogant in your ſelves) <hi>that partly obſtinacy is come to Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, until the fulneſs of the Gentiles be come in: And ſo all Iſrael ſhall be ſaved,</hi> as it is written, Iſa. 59. and 27.9. and Jer. 31.33, 34. Heb. 8. and 10. I have next to offer to your conſiderations, the many promiſes made by God by the mouthes of his Prophets, for the reduction of them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their own countrey, ſtill owning them for his own peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, a countrey, I ſay, lawfully theirs, by the donation of God himſelf, and a propriety, that no Prince under Heaven can plead the like, the promiſes alſo ſetting forth the reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the pure worſhip of God, the reſtitution of all things to their primitive Eſtate, <hi>That the earth ſhall be full of the knowledge of the Lord, as the waters cover the ſea,</hi> Iſa. 11.49. &amp; 60. &amp; 61. to the end of the Propheſie; beſides many more places in this and other Prophets, ſome where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of do more plainly extend to the advantage of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.6. <hi>And the ſtrangers that cleave unto the Lord, to ſerve him, and to love the name of Jehovah, to be his ſervants; every one that keepeth the Sabbath from poluting it, and takes hold on my Covenant, Even them will I bring to my holy mountain, and make them joyful in my houſe of prayer; their burnt-offerings and their ſacrifices ſhall be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted upon mine altar, for mine houſe ſhall be called an houſe of prayer for all peoples;</hi> And conſequently for us (the faithful) as well as for the Jews.</p>
            <p>Now weighing well with our ſelves both theſe threats and promiſes, were it not a ſtrange negligence (I conceive it a madneſs) in us to forego ſo great priviledges, as by thoſe honorable people of the Jews may accrew unto us, and as great wilfulneſs to lay our ſelves open to thoſe judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments threatned, I leave to the judgement of all men that are any thing affected in this matter, or that tender the glory of God, their own good charity towards that the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115300:5"/>people of God: We have great and important cauſe to take heed, leſt we of this Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> putting from us and abandoning theſe people of God, we ſeparate not our ſelves from Gods favor and protection, this being a greater aggravation of the ſin, for that it is now more known. It is not tollerable even amongſt Moral men, if we go no further, to adde affliction to the afflicted, as we do in continuing Laws in force againſt them; it ſtands not with a generous ſpirit, to triumph over a man helpleſs and in miſery, much more hateful is it in men that profeſs themſelves the ſervants of god; but rather that we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavor to comfort them, and (if it were poſſible) to give them ſatisfaction for the innocent blood of theirs ſhed in this Kingdom, and to reſtore them to commerce a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us.</p>
            <p>It is objected, That many of theſe propheſies have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the ſeventy years Captivity, and their releaſe from <hi>Babylon,</hi> and of Gods vengeance on the Enemies of the people of God of thoſe times. In Anſwer, Although ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny propheſies do ſo, yet the places abovementioned, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny moe, do abundantly prove the reduction of all the houſe of Iſrael, the ten Tribes never yet returned into their own Land, and the great joy that is promiſed them in thoſe yet future bleſſed times, as <hi>Hoſea</hi> 3. they are eſteemed by God, as the ſpouſe to the husband, and in the laſt Verſe, <hi>After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſhall the children of Iſrael return, and ſeek the Lord, and David their King, and ſhall fear the Lord and his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the latter days;</hi> And <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36. the Prophet is directed to the whole houſe of Iſrael, as appears more plainly in the 10 Verſe, <hi>And I will multiply the men upon you</hi> (ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the mountains of Iſrael all along before) <hi>even all the houſe of Iſrael wholly, and the Cities ſhall be inhabited, &amp;c.</hi> And a much more luculent place is the 37 Chapter of <hi>Ezek.</hi> where mention is made of the return of all the Tribes of Iſrael, the Prophet being commanded to take a piece of wood, and to write upon that to <hi>Judah,</hi> and the children
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115300:5"/>of Iſrael his companions, and then to take another piece of wood, and write upon that to <hi>Joſeph,</hi> the tree of <hi>Ephra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im,</hi> and all the houſe of Iſrael his companions, and joyn them one to another into one ſtick, and they ſhall become one ſtick in thine hand; <hi>And when the children of thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhall ſpeak unto thee, ſaying, Wilt thou not ſhew us what thou meaneſt by theſe? ſay unto them, Thus ſaith Jehovah God, Behold, I will take the ſtick of Joſeph, which is in the hand of Ephraim, and the Tribes of Iſrael his fellows, and will put them with him, even with the ſtick of Judah, and make them one ſtick, and they ſhall be one in mine hand; And the ſticks whereon thou writest, ſhall be in thine hand before their eyes: And ſay unto them, Thus ſaith Jehovah God, Behold, I will take the children of Iſrael from among the Heathen whither they be gone, and will gather them on every ſide, and bring them into their own Land: And I will make them one Nation in the Land, upon the mountains of Iſrael, and one King ſhall be King to them all; And they ſhall be no more two Nations, neither ſhall they be divided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to two kingdoms any more at all, neither ſhall they defile them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves any more with their idols,</hi> &amp;c. Theſe words are an explanation of the parable of the dry bones in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Chapter; whereby part of my purpoſe is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently proved, that their reſtauration and inhabitation of their countrey here on Earth, is yet to be fulfilled; for the ten Tribes that were firſt captivated by <hi>Shalmanezzar,</hi> never yet returned to this day, which yet ſhall be in the time ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by God, and conſequently their oppreſſors bear the greater and notorious ſin, undervaluing a people to whom God hath made ſuch precious promiſes. And whereas it is again Objected, That theſe places of the ſeveral Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, do intend the ſtate of the Church triumphant, of the new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> conceived to be in Heaven after the day of Judgement, and that theſe places have a myſtical ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in them, mentioning <hi>David</hi> to be their King, who was a type of Chriſt. Anſwer, doubtleſs God hath given us the Scriptures for our inſtruction and edification, and hath
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115300:6"/>given us reaſonable ſouls, underſtanding, and other faculties, it were ſtrange then that there ſhould be a literal conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of theſe places following, which are ſo adapted to the underſtanding of even the ſimpleſt, that nothing can be more clear: <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 65.21, 22. ſpeaking of the Jews return. <hi>And they ſhall build houſes and inhabite them, and they ſhall plant vineyards, and eat the fruit of them; They ſhall not build, and another inhabite, they ſhall not plant, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eat: For as the days of a tree, are the days of my people, and mine elect ſhall enjoy in old age the work of their hands:</hi> and Zech. 8.5. <hi>Thus ſaith Jehovah of hoſts, there ſhall yet old men and old women dwell in the ſtreets of Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, and every man with his ſtaff in his hand for very age: and the ſtreets of the city ſhall be full of boyes and girls, play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the ſtreets thereof:</hi> and Ezek. 28.26. <hi>And they ſhall dwel ſafely therein, and ſhal build houſes, and plant vineyards; yea, they ſhall dwell ſafely, when I have executed judgements upon all round about them that deſpiſe them, &amp; they ſhal know that I am Jehovah their God:</hi> and Micah 4.4. and Jer. 31. and Zech. 10.6. and 12.6. with many more pregnant places. As theſe Scriptures do moſt plainly ſet forth and prove their reinhabitation of their countrey, ſo it proves that the ſame hath not been yet fulfilled, for after their return from <hi>Babylon,</hi> we know how their countrey hath been deſolated by the invaſion of their Enemies, and how often by many Nations, as it continues to this day. It is further Objected, that in divers places mention is made of <hi>David</hi> to be their King for ever, who is held a type of Chriſt, and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it ſeems to allude to the future eſtates of the Saints in Heaven. Anſwer, though mention be made of <hi>Davids</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Prince for ever, and of their dwelling in their Land for ever, yet I conceive thoſe places do not conclude the eſtates of the Saints in Heaven, for it is ſaid in <hi>Jer.</hi> 30.21. <hi>And their noble ruler ſhall be of themſelves, and their governors ſhall proceed from the midſt of them; and I will cauſe him to draw near and approach unto me:</hi> We know that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115300:6"/>this Propheſie was long ſince <hi>Davids</hi> time, and therefore how this future kingdom ſhall be inſtituted, God onely knows, which he will reveal in due time: 'Tis plainly proved by other places that they ſhall enjoy their honor here on Earth, and in the ſight of the Heathen (their oppreſſors) which doth plainly imply, that it ſhall be here on Earth that the Jews ſhall enjoy this bleſſing and deliverance, &amp;c. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 28.25. Alſo we read <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.36. <hi>If theſe ordinances depart out of my ſight, ſaith Jehovah, then ſhall the ſeed of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael ceaſe from being a nation before me for ever:</hi> So that their: continuance to be a Nation, proves a terreſtrial eſtate; whatſoever additions of glory, and priviledges fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God will confer on them: Commentators have their ſeveral judgements herein (and differ among themſelves) yet whatſoever they ſay, I conceive we have no warrant to wreſt thoſe Scriptures onely to a ſpiritual ſence, unleſs they do repugn ſome known truth of God in the Scripture. Since theſe things are ſo, How far are we from that godly zeal of thoſe people of God of the Gentiles, that ſhall bring the beloved Jews in their arms, and their daughters on their ſhoulders, when Kings ſhall be their nurſing fathers, and Queens their nurſes, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.22, 23.</p>
            <p>The rage of men in all countries of the world have been very extreme againſt the Jews, 'tis not ſo much wonder to ſee the barbarous Infidels, robbing them and embruing their hands in their blood, as that men that profeſs more of Gods truth (though falſly:) In <hi>Spain</hi> there were 120000 Jews caſt out and baniſht, in the year 1493. In <hi>Italy</hi> and other places, the like hardſhip they have endured.</p>
            <p>But I hope better things of our Nation, that when our troubles at home by Gods mercy are compoſed, there are many gallant men now in arms, and others that may be inſtrumental for the beating down Gods Enemies, and the Enemies of his people: Gods power is enough, and who ſhall let it; yet he uſually works by means, and who knows but theſe now in arms may have the honor to do
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115300:7"/>Gods work herein; I am ſure 'tis to be wiſhed, that we wraſtle with God by Prayer, that this deſign for Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and his people may be advanced; and that our weapons (when quiet here at home) may be bent againſt the cruel op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſors of his people in forraign parts, and thoſe mercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Tyrants ſo rigorous towards the Jews where they are, vexing them, and ſpoiling them of their lives and lively<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood; <hi>That at the laſt we may beat our ſwords into plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhares, and our ſpears into pruning-hooks; when Nation ſhall not lift up ſword againſt Nation, neither ſhall they learn war any more,</hi> Iſaiah 2.4. I truſt God will direct his inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in their proceedings to this great deliverance (who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they be) in juſt and righteous ways, and will crown thoſe actions that are built on juſt foundations: When <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> built the temple in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> it was ordered that the Timber and ſtone was hewen and prepared in <hi>Lebanon,</hi> that noiſe of hewing being not heard, at the erecting of that glorious Houſe for Gods worſhip; what mean out late tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults and blooſhed then? as a reverend Preacher (now deceaſed) well obſerved, Sith God will do his own work his own way, and by his own onely power, but this may be the hewing and working in <hi>Lebanon</hi> which we have heard; it behoves then all the Servants of God ſo to approve their hearts to him, that when the Lord comes with Refiners fire, and Fullers ſope, ſuch inſtruments may have the bleſſing to be exact in Gods work, that others imployed hereafter outdo them not, howſoever there are many infirmities in the beſt, yet is it their duty to ſtrive for perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>Whereas I ſtile them honorable, though it may ſeem ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous to their Enemies, and the ignorant; yet I may truly ſay, They are of the higheſt and moſt honorable deſcent of any Nobility in any Countrey in the world, being ennobled by God himſelf, and the reaſon is given which muſt be moſt righteous; not for any thing in them, or for their multitude, but becauſe God ſet his love upon them. We ſee Princes fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorites
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115300:7"/>are much courted, there's much more reaſon that Gods favor ſhould attract a greater reſpect to theſe ſons of Iſrael then they have: God made good his promiſe made to <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> who deſcended from <hi>Sem</hi> the choice and beloved ſeed: The works and wonders God ſhewed in their deliverance out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> honoring them with his preſence, <hi>and leading them by a pillar of a cloud by day, and alpillar of fire by night:</hi> Why ſhould then the great Princes and Nobles of the world, ſo much mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie themſelves, for their ancient and honorable deſcent, whereas the Jews were Gods choſen people and beloved, and deſcended from the moſt holy men of God, account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Princes and Prophets in their times, and of the Kings of <hi>Judah,</hi> whereof there were more Religions Princes, then of any Kingdom we read of in all ages or Nations? And this I believe to be true Nobility, having God to ratifie it. The Gentile Princes had the beginnings of their greatneſs by the Sword, Tyranny and Policy, moſt ordinarily, as the Turks now, and the Romans of old, and others; And what challenge can they (yea, more legitimate Princes then they) make from Gods diſpenſation, in compariſon of the Jews: And though the Jews have contracted a great guilt, for their unthankfulneſs for the peculiar bleſſings given them of God, and other grievous ſins; yet when God, who is Lord over all, and againſt whom their ſins were committed, ſhall acquit them of this guilt, pronouncing, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.1, 2. <hi>That her warfare is accompliſhed, that her ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity is pardoned, and that ſhe hath received of the Lords hand double for all her ſins:</hi> Why then ſhould Princes and their great nobility, both which are but the progeny of Princes of a lower degree then <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>David?</hi> fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, why ſhould the Pope and his Cardinals, with their Clergy, that are but impoſtors, and have cheated the whole world, and but upſtarts of baſe degree, why ſhould all theſe? and what have they to challenge to themſelves, to be ſo hard maſters to thoſe honorable people, of whom
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115300:8"/>God hath pronounced, That the Jews ſhal be feared of them whoſe ſervants they were.</p>
            <p>I know the great impugners of this Apology for the Jews will be the Pope and his Clergy, and of them the Jeſuits, his principal Agents, for that this oppoſeth their chief princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the political upholding of the Papacy and themſelves; and its no wonder, their cruelties ſhewed upon them, and their deteſtation of them is ſuch, that in <hi>Italy</hi> (though they are allowed ſome commerce, which the Italians do for their own profit they make by the Jews divers ways) yet the enjoyn them to wear apparel, of colour diſtinct from other people, inſomuch that men abhor the wearing of a red Hat, leaſt they ſhould be accounted Jews. The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts are eſpecially offended with them, becauſe the Jews ſo much abhor the Imagery and Idolatrous Worſhip of theirs, for touch that, and touch the corner ſtone of their Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique foundation: The Jeſuits do neſtle into all Kingdoms and States of Chriſtendom, and have an influence on their Counſels, as alſo of Univerſities, Armies, great Cities and Corporations, wherein they imploy the choyceſt wits they have, who undertake any kinde of profeſſions, the better to cloak their deſigns; as Gentlemen, Divines, Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians, Soldiers. It is moſt heartily wiſhed, and now hoped for, that their <hi>Cyrens</hi> Songs ſhall not inchant the ears of the godly, whatſoever they may work on carnal Politicians and Hypocrites.</p>
            <p>I humbly offer this Apology, with theſe conſiderations, to the whole Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> from the higheſt to the loweſt, that as God hath exceedingly bleſſed this Kingdom above others, eſpecially in this, that it hath been almoſt One hundred years, the chief Bulwark for defence of the Truth, and retreat of the afflicted in Europe; ſo now that we all ſhew our ſelves compaſſionate and helpers of the afflicted Jews; and pray, that the ſame Authority that proceeded againſt them formerly, that now the ſame power and authority will repeal thoſe ſevere Laws made againſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115300:8"/>them: That our receiving them again, and giving them all poſſible ſatisfaction, and reſtoring them to commerce in this kingdom, may be exemplary to other Nations that have done them, and continue to do them wrong; till which time (God putting their tears into his bottle) God will charge their ſufferings upon us, and will avenge them on their perſecuters.</p>
            <p>And what I have now written, was not upon any mans motion of the Jews Nation, but a thing that I have long and deeply revolved within my heart; but truly and indeed, my endeavors are for the glory of God, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of thoſe his afflicted people, the love of my own ſweet native countrey of <hi>England,</hi> and the freeing of my own ſoul in the day of account; for I thought my ſelf obliged in conſcience, to publiſh my conceptions herein; and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, do moſt earneſtly pray, That the potent par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties may no longer continue in diviſion, but denying all Councels of the fleſh, the acquiring of Honors, and all ſelf-ends, may ingenuouſly confeſs themſelves and their failings one to another, and dealing with lenity one towards ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and humbled before Jehovah, may obtain remiſſion of our ſins and miſeries, and a bleſſing from God be ſhowed down upon us, which God Almighty of his infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite mercy grant.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
